We've talked a lot about moving data, methods,
computed, all of you've done that successfully.
But the one thing I've intentioned left off
because it's kind of different in the script setup
is the idea of basically what are compiler macros.
So what are compiler macros?
Well, let's go ahead and open up the nav bar here.
And so let me go ahead and now hide this.
Yeah, perfect, okay.
So let's go ahead and convert this over to TypeScript rule quick.
So the script set up, laying TS, and then to do, save,
that's gone, that's gone.
Okay, we're going to comment out the props for a second,
and then we're just going to quickly say,
cons, nav list equals a ref and wrap it just like that.
And so here's an example, right where we're progressively
enhancing a, well, I have the wrong thing here.
Here we go.
We're progressively enhancing the component
you can see here with TypeScript, but you'll notice, though,
that, actually let me import ref real quick,
so that y'all can not be distracted by the Reich's quickly.
I'm actually, I'm not actually going out of my way
to define a custom type for what is inside of this nav list.
Because, first of all, at this moment,
it's fairly straightforward, and if we look at the ref,
it already knows it's a name and a path.
Now granted, if over time you start building,
like nav items, and you want it to follow a specific structure,
there's only a rationale to do so.
But this is where it's important to try to differentiate
when something is valuable to you,
and versus when something is just done
for the sake of purity, for purity sake.
Now, that said, we still haven't defined this props, though,
and how do we do that?
And so compiler macros, essentially,
are a views way of providing you functionality
that will not impact the bundle that's ultimately outputted.
And so we have this, basically, a helper function
called defined props.
And this, again, once again, this function
is a compiler macro that's specific to script setup.
So you actually can't use this, or you shouldn't really
be using it outside of setup.
And so inside of this defined props, what we can do
is similarly to how we normally define props,
we can just say tagline, and then we can do things
like type string and require true.
So this is where defined props, this looks pretty familiar.
So we take that concept now, and let's look at something
a little bit more advanced.
Let's go ahead and take a look at the restaurant card.
Here is where we can actually start to, yeah,
let's play with this one.
OK.
So on the restaurant card, you'll see here
that we have a prop that's a complex type,
it's an object that is supposed to be a restaurant.
And it also has this emit thing, which we'll talk about in a second.
And then, otherwise, we need to go ahead and move this over.
So let's go and do that real quick.
We'll have setup, we'll take care of that.
Let's comment this block out first.
And then once here, we have constatus color, equals computed,
wrap that arrow function, that's it.
And then here, we have our delete restaurant,
and then that is a function.
And then we will comment this out for a second
because this won't work.
OK.
So here we have everything.
And so using what we just learned about compiler macros,
we said that there was a defined props helper method.
And so one of the things we could do
is we could do the same thing as before.
We could say restaurant, and it's a type,
object, as prop, type, restaurant.
And then we can say required true.
This seems, this is familiar.
But what if we wanted to do this a little bit more
like natural type script?
Well, one of the things we can do is we
can actually provide the types to define props as a basically
do type casting.
So in other words, we could, for example,
call it prop types, I'll just call it like that.
And we say there is a thing called a restaurant
that is of type restaurant, just like that.
And so the way this will look inside of your props
is rather than defining it inside of the parameters
of the parentheses, we use the greater than less than
simple brackets, and then you just pass in prop types.
And then this provides you a little bit more
of that organic type script feel.
However, one of the things you might be thinking of
is, well, OK, so for example, here we,
this is pure type script world.
So we can't just go like, oh, this is actually
type restaurant, and we can't be required true default,
whatever.
This is not going to work.
Because this is not an actual JavaScript object.
So if you want to use something that's required,
remember that inside of type script, as long as you define
a property on an object, it's by default required.
So that's already on.
If you actually want it to be optional, then this is where
you might put the question mark as part of it.
I'll actually not go whoops, I forgot.
Sorry, go back here.
You would want to put it like this.
And then you're saying that this prop is optional
and not required on the component.
The thing, though, is that something that we often do
when it comes to props is we want a default value.
And so this is something that's currently
in an experimental phase, but I'll show you how
I've seen some of it done before.
So there's two ways to do this.
One is that there is, I forgot which build this was,
but at one point, there was a proposition to do it like this,
where you had this use defaults or use with defaults helper.
And then you would pass in another object that was like
restaurant and then like default values.
For me, this is kind of clunky, because you have this defined
props, and you're wrapping it with use with default
that you're passing in a second argument that happens
to be it feels a little clunky.
So the way that's currently being experimented with here
in the docs, which I'll definitely link to,
is let me blow it up a little bit,
is it's basically reactive destructuring.
So basically, you would actually define your props as normal.
But then, as a result of using normal JavaScript,
where you destruct the props that you would normally
want to use, you just assigned the default values then,
which is actually fairly one to one with actually
what we come to expect with JavaScript, actually.
And so granted, again, at least at the time of this recording,
this is an experimental feature that needs opt-in inside
of your build.
But this is the direction, it looks like this
is the direction that view three is heading,
as far as using defined props so that you
can provide default values.
In the meantime, though, if you really want,
basically, what I would recommend just
to keep things simple, that I delete it, I did delete it.
Is while the casting is nice, I honestly don't,
I think for the most part, it's totally fine to just keep it
as is to just say restaurant type, the object
has prop, type, restaurant, and then just
a find your default here as part of your definition.
There's nothing wrong with this.
Again, we'll find better ways to doing it.
But for now, if you really do want to default,
this is one way to do it.
That said, there's nothing stopping you as well
from assigning another reactive value that will then
take the prop if it's empty set it.
As we know, programming, there's
a lot of different ways to do things.
So don't feel tied in, but for now,
we're going to assume there's no default.
So it's totally fine, which just uses typecasting
to do define props.
OK, so I'm going to delete that, I can delete that.
OK, now we've defined our props.
And then actually, one sec, I need to actually import
it, compute it, so this thing stops yelling at me.
And then we have, OK, here's the next problem, though.
You'll notice though that inside of Options API,
we typically could refer to the props directly
because it was on the disk object.
It was automatically inherited.
But that's no longer the case, because we have it
where we have it inside of defined props.
So how do we get access to it?
Well, we create a variable that we want to reference.
So typically, it's just consprops.
That's simple.
And then that way, the this becomes props.resherent.status.
And so you'll see though, which is just interestingly enough,
is that typefrib is yelling at us.
It's saying that, hey, as a right now,
based on how you define the props, it
might actually be undefined.
So I can actually run this block of code.
And so this is where typeguards come into play.
So if we want, we could say, if props.resherent exists,
then run all this code, right?
And then, as you can see here, with that typeguard,
typefrib knows that it can assume that typefresh
on what have it's all the properties that it needs,
and then it can run through.
And that's actually helpful because, as we know,
when you build your codes and times,
you we do miss these little edge cases and things do break,
because we forgot that like, oh, yeah, in this particular data
type, something like this needs to happen before something
like this happens, typefrib does help you to kind of
remind you of that.
However, in our case, this is a required prop.
So in that case, the typeguard is really not necessary.
So this way, you can see it's not yelling at me,
because I'm promising it that it will get the value that it wants.